American Foreign Service Association Records
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
American Foreign Service Association Records 1940-1964
MSS21071
American Foreign Service Association
4,000 items 13 containers 5.2 linear feet
Manuscript Division Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Correspondence, articles, memoranda, editorials, essays, photographs, newspaper clippings, and printed matter pertaining to the publication of the American Foreign Service Journal issued in Washington, D.C., by the American Foreign Service Association, also known as the Foreign Service Association.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the Library's online catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically therein.
People
Briggs, Ellis, 1899-1976--Correspondence.; Craig, Gordon Alexander, 1913- --Correspondence.; De Wolf, Francis Colt, 1894- --Correspondence.; Estabrook, Robert H.--Correspondence.; Kennan, George F. (George Frost), 1904-2005.; Rubenstein, Lewis W. (Lewis William), 1908- --Correspondence.; Skinner, Robert Peet, 1866-1960--Correspondence.; Villard, Henry Serrano, 1900- --Correspondence.; Wiggins, James Russell, 1903-2000--Correspondence.; Wriston, Henry M. (Henry Merritt), 1889-1978--Correspondence.
Organizations
American Foreign Service Association.
Subjects
Diplomatic and consular service, American--Periodicals.; Diplomatic and consular service, American.
Titles
American foreign service journal.
Administrative Information
Provenance
The records of American Foreign Service Association were given to the Library of Congress by the association in 1964.
Access and Restrictions
The records of American Foreign Service Association are open to research. Researchers are advised to contact the Manuscript Reading Room prior to visiting. Many collections are stored off-site and advance notice is needed to retrieve these items for research use.
Scope and Content Note
The records of the American Foreign Service Association span the years 1940-1964 and consist of editorial correspondence, articles, memoranda, editorials, essays, photographs, newspaper clippings, and printed matter pertaining to the publication of the American Foreign Service Journal issued in Washington, D.C., by the American Foreign Service Association, also known as the Foreign Service Association.
The Correspondence series features letters with foreign service officers of all ranks, State Department officials, publishing houses, advertisers, and contributors. Correspondents include Ellis Ormsbee Briggs, Gordon Alexander Craig, Francis Colt De Wolf, Robert H. Estabrook, George F. Kennan, Lewis Rubenstein, Robert Peet Skinner, Henry Serrano Villard, James Russell Wiggins, and Henry M. Wriston.
The Essay Contests series relates to writing contests sponsored by the association in 1940 and 1944. The contest in 1940 asked officers to describe unusual or amusing events and incidents they had witnessed or an experience of an extraordinary or dramatic character. Essays in 1944 were submitted under the title "Suggestions for Improving the Foreign Service and Its Administration to Meet Its War and Postwar Responsibilities."
Arrangement of the Records
This collection is arranged in two series:
Correspondence, 1950-1964
Essay Contests, 1940-1944
http://lccn.loc.gov/mm81021071
Container List
- Correspondence, 1950-1964 (Box 1-11)
  Editorial correspondence including comments, essays, articles, editorials, memoranda, newspaper clippings, printed matter, and photographs.
  Arranged in an alphabetical file for 1950-1962 and a chronological file for 1962-1964.
  - Alphabetical, 1950-1962 (Box 1-11)
    - A-B, (14 folders) (Box 1)
    - C-E, (11 folders) (Box 2)
    - E-H, (11 folders) (Box 3)
    - H-L, (14 folders) (Box 4)
    - L-N, (14 folders) (Box 5)
    - O-R, (11 folders) (Box 6)
    - R-S, (11 folders) (Box 7)
    - S, (8 folders) (Box 8, Box 9)
    - T-W, (14 folders) (Box 10)
    - W-Z, (6 folders) (Box 11)
  - Chronological, 1962-1964, (12 folders) (Box 11)
- Essay Contests, 1940-1944 (Box 12-13)
  Essays submitted for publication by foreign service officers as part of writing contests in 1940 and 1944, together with correspondence, memoranda, editorial sheets, and other material.
  Arranged by year of contest.
  - 1940, (4 folders) (Box 12)
  - 1944, (7 folders); (12 folders) (Box 12, Box 13)